Paul M. Roca Papers and Photographs, 1887-1979 (bulk 1955-1977)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Paul M. Roca Papers and Photographs, 1887-1979 (bulk 1955-1977)
MS 531
Roca, Paul M.
The Paul M. Roca Papers and Photographs contains materials which document Jesuit churches throughout the Northern Mexico states of Sonora and Chihuahua. The collection consists of two series, Photographs and Papers. The first series, Photographs (1887-1965, bulk 1955-1965) consists of 156 photographs featured in Paths of the Padres through Sonora: An Illustrated History & Guide to Its Spanish Churches published by the Arizona Pioneers’ Historical Society in 1967 with accompanying maps. The second series, Papers (1977), contains 4 manuscript versions of Spanish Jesuit Churches in Mexico’s Tarahumara published by the University of Arizona Press in 1979. A selection of Roca’s images have been posted on History Pin: Paul Roca Photographs of Missions in Sonora, Mexico.
2.0 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Paul McClennan Roca (1912-1979) had a strong bond to the areas of the American Southwest and Northern States of Mexico. His Chilean grandfather, Miguel G. Roca, settled in Mexico where he married Josefa Samaniego y Bustamante de Haro who was from a long-standing family linked to the Mexican states of Sonora and Chihuahua. Their son, Lautaro Roca, met and married Stella McClennan in Mexico. Lautaro was a silver-mine operator and Stella was an art teacher who worked with the children of a hacienda owner in Durango. They were eventually forced to move due to the political unrest of the Mexican Revolution and physical limitations resulting from uncooperative weather. The Rocas re-located to Nebraska, Stella’s home state, where Paul M. Roca was born. The Rocas eventually returned to the Southwest and settled in Tucson, Arizona where Paul M. Roca grew up and attended public school. Roca was a 1933 Honors graduate of the University of Arizona and in 1941 graduated with distinction from the George Washington Law School. Roca, a prominent lawyer, co-founded the firm of Lewis Roca Rothgerber in 1950 and practiced law in Arizona until the time of his death in 1979.
Roca spent a great deal of his lifetime collecting books and manuscripts related to the Arizona, Southwestern history, and the history of the Jesuit years in Sonora and Chihuahua. During most of the 1930s and 1940s, Roca was the chief administrative assistant to U.S. Senator Carl Hayden who had a significant influence on Roca’s interest in the Southwestern United States and Northern Mexico. For over 20 years, Roca traveled back and forth between the United States and various locations in Northern Mexico to document Jesuit churches and church ruins. He wrote two books related to this subject. The first was Paths of the Padres through Sonora: An Illustrated History & Guide to Its Spanish Churches published by the Arizona Pioneers’ Historical Society in 1967 and the second was Spanish Jesuit Churches in Mexico’s Tarahumara published by the University of Arizona Press in 1979.
At the time of his death, Paul M. Roca had been working on a third manuscript relating to Jesuit churches in the Chínipas Mountains in Chihuahua. The photo negatives related to the unfinished manuscript were donated to the Arizona State Museum.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series.
Series I:Photographs 1887-1965 (bulk 1955-1965)
Series II:Papers 1977
Scope and Content Note
The collection (1888-1977) contains 156 photographs featured in the book, Paths of the Padres through Sonora: An Illustrated History & Guide to Its Spanish Churches, and four copies of a single manuscript, Spanish Jesuit Churches in Mexico’s Tarahumara. The Photograph Series (1887-1965, bulk 1955-1965) contains 156 photographs and corresponding maps denoting the approximate location of the churches. Most photos are by Roca, but in the case of other photographers they have been attributed in the folder title. The Papers series (1977) is comprised of four drafts of Spanish Jesuit Churches in Mexico’s Tarahumara: one typed draft with paste-ups, one unedited photocopy, one photocopy edited by both Karen Shure, an editor at the University of Arizona Press, and Roca himself, and one final photocopy sent to the University of Arizona Press.
A History Pin featuring 30 of the collection photographs was created
Additional manuscripts and negatives by Paul M. Roca are located at the Arizona State Museum: Paul M. Roca Northern Mexico Mission Research Files.
Access Terms
Roca, Paul M.
Architecture, Colonial -- Mexico -- Chihuahua (State)
Church architecture -- Mexico -- Chihuahua (State)
Jesuit architecture -- Mexico -- Chihuahua (State)
Missionaries -- Mexico – Biography
Missions -- Mexico-- Sonora (State)
Missions, Spanish -- Mexico -- Sonora (State)
Tarahumara architecture
Chihuahua (Mexico: State)
Sonora (Mexico: State)
United States --Arizona
Maps
Photography
Container List
- Series 1: Photographs, 1887-1965; (bulk 1955-1965)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by mission name. It contains photographs of churches and maps denoting the location of the churches featured in Paths of the Padres through Sonora: An Illustrated History & Guide to Its Spanish Churches.
  - A Home, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - La Asunción de Nuestra Señora de Rahun, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bamoa, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - La Capilla de Nuestra Señora de los Dolores de Batuc, 1959 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - La Capilla de Nuestra Señora de Zapopán del Real de los Alamos, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - La Capilla de Oposura, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - La Capilla de San Juan Evangelista de Huachinera by Alfred Cohn, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carrizal, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chinipas, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Choix, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - La Colorada, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Los Dulces Nombres del Valle de Tacupeto, 1961 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - El Espíritu Santo de Cocorit, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Espíritu Santo de Etchojoa, 1962 October (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - El Fuerte, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Guazápares, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Motepore, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nío, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Nuestra Señora de Balbanera de la Aduana, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Nuestra Señora de Guadalupe de Mazatán, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Nuestra Señora de Guadalupe de Tayopa, 1964 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nuestra Señora de Guadalupe de Teuricachi, 1960 October (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Nuestra Señora de Guadalupe la Reina de Los Ángeles, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Nuestra Señora de la Asunción de Álamos, 1959 October (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Nuestra Señora de la Asunción de Arizpe by Robert Creighton, 1958 April (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Nuestra Señora de la Asunción de Arizpe, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Nuestra Señora de la Asunción de Bacerac, 1959 April (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Nuestra Señora de la Asunción de Opodepe, 1959 April (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Nuestra Señora de Loreto de Nátora, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Nuestra Señora de Loreto de Sátachi, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Nuestra Señora de Loreto del Real de Baroyeca, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Nuestra Señora de los Dolores de Cósari, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Nuestra Señora de los Remedios Banámichi, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Nuestra Señora de los Remedios de Doágibubig, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Nuestra Señora del Pópulo, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Nuestra Señora del Rosario de Bámori, 1961 May (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Nuestra Señora del Rosario de Nocozari, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Bacanora, 1959 April (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Cáborica, 1964 September (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Cuquiárachi, 1959 April (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Móchapa, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Sinoquipe, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Nuestro Padre San Ignacio de Suaqui Grande, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - La Purísma Concepción de Baviácora, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - San Ambrosio de Búsanic by Harry J. Karnes, 1933-1943 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - San Ambrosio de Búsanic, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - San Antonio de Hermosillo, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - San Antonio de la Arizona, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - San Bartolo de Batacosa, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - San Bernadino de Awátobi by Peabody Museum, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - San Bernardo de Aquimuri, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - San Clemente de Térarpa, 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - San Diego del Pitiquito by A.E. Lippincott, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - San Estanislao del Ootcam, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - San Felipe Gracia Real de Terrenate, 1964 September (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - San Francisco de Asís del Río Chico, 1960 April (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - San Francisco de Borja de Tecoripa, 1959 October (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - San Francisco de Regis del Presidio Real de San Carlos Buenavista, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - San Francisco de Regis del Presidio Real de San Carlos Buenavista by Tad Nichols, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - San Francisco del Átil by Prent Duell, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 60>)
  - San Francisco del Átil, 1958 April (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - San Francisco Javier de Arivechi, 1959 April (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - San Francisco Javier de Cuchuta, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - San Francisco Javier de Huásabas by Byron Ivancovich, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - San Francisco Javier de Maicoba, 1961 May (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - San Francisco Javier de Maicoba, 1961 May (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - San Ignacio de Cuirimpo, 1962 October (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - San Ignacio de Suaqui (de Batuc), 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - San Ignacio de Tesia, 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - San Ildefonso de Ostímuri, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - San Joaquín y Santa Ana de Nuri, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - San Joaquín y Santa Ana de Tepache, 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - San Joaquín y Santa Ana de Tepache, 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - San José de Batepito, 1962 April (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - San José de Gracia, 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - San José de los Pimas, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - San José de Soyopa, 1959 October (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - San Juan Bautista de Saracachi, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - San Juan Bautista de Sonora, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - San Juan Evangelista de Huachinera, 1959 October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - San Iázaro, 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - San Iorenzo de Huépac by Pbro. Ernesto López, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - San Iorenzo de Huépac, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - San Lucas Nuevo de Agiobampo by Harry J. Karns, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - San Luís de Bacoancos, 1933-1943 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - San Luís de Bacoancos, 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - San Marcelo de Sonoýta, 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - San Marco Picháchic, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - San Mateo de Malzura, 1962 October (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - San Miguel Arcángel de Horcasitas, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - San Miguel Arcángel de los Ures, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - San Miguel Arcángel de Oposura, 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - San Miguel de Bacoachi, 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - San Miguel de Bavispe, circa 1887 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - San Miguel de Bavispe, 1959 October (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - San Miguel de Belén, 1962 October (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - San Miguel de Belén, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - San Miguel de Macoyahui, 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - San Miguel de Tuape, 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - San Miguel del Tupo, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - San Miguelito, 1962 April (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - San Pablo de Quíburi, 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - San Pablo Pescadero, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - San Pedro de Aconchi, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - San Pedro de Cumuripa, 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - San Pedro de Tonibavi, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - San Simon y San Judas Tadeo del Síboda, 1961 May (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - San Valentín de Bísani, 1933-1943 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - San Valentín de Bísani, 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Santa Ana (Vieja), 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Santa Ana, 1961 May (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Santa Ana, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Santa Cruz (Suamea), 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Santa Cruz de Bácum, 1959 October (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Santa Cruz de Mayo, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Santa Cruz de Nácori, 1962 October (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Santa Gertrudis del Altar, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Santa Gertrudis del Sáric, 1961 December (Box 2, Folder 52>)
  - Santa Gertudis de Tepodéhuachi, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Santa Magdalena de los Tepocas, 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Santa María de Movas, 1960 April (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Santa María de Movas, 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Santa María de Nacámeri (now Rayón), 1959 April (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Santa María de Nácori Chico, 1962 April (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Santa Maríía de Tepupa, 1959 April (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Santa María del Pópulo de Tónichi, 1959 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Santa María Nuestra Señora de Navojoa, 1963 October (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Santa María Purísima de Pónida, 1959 April (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Santa Rosa de Corodéhuachi, 1960 October (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Santa Rosa de los Pimas, 1964 September (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Santa Rosa de Tevidéhuachi, 1964 September (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Santa Rosalía, 1962 April (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Santa Rosalía de Onapa, 1961 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Santa Teresa del Adid, 1961 December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - La Santísima Trinidad, Sonora, 1965 October (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Santísima Trinidad de Huatabampo, 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Santísima Trinidad de Júpari, 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - La Santísima Trinidad de Vícam, 1959 October (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - La Santísima Trinidad del Pitic, 1961 May (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Santo Tomás, 1959 April (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Santo Tomás Apóstol de Serva, 1962 April (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Los Santos Ángeles de Guévavi by George S. Roskruge, 1889 July (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Los Santos Ángeles de Guévavi by William O’Brien, 1960 May (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Los Santos Reyes de Cucurpe, 1959 April (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Señor San José de Chinapa, 1960 April (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Señor San José de Guaymas, 1959 October (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Señor San José de Mátape, 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - El Señor San José de Minas Nuevas, 1963 October (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Senor San José de Teópare, 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sinaloa, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Sisoguíchic, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Tayopa (Mulatos), 1965 October (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Vaca, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - La Virgen de Guadalupe de Yécora, 1960 April (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series 2: Papers, 1977
  Contains four separate drafts of Spanish Jesuit Churches in Mexico’s Tarahumara. Each draft has been broken into smaller sections.
  - Typed-Draft with Paste-Ups: Introduction-page 124, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Typed-Draft with Paste-Ups: Pages 125-237, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Typed-Draft with Paste-Ups: Pages 238-316, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Typed-Draft with Paste-Ups: Pages 317-423, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Unedited Copy: Introduction-Page 111, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Unedited Copy: Pages 112-242, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Unedited Copy: Pages 210-404, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Edited Copy with Comments by Karen Shure and Roca: Introduction-Page 99, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Edited Copy with Comments by Karen Shure and Roca: Pages 100-209, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Edited Copy with Comments by Karen Shure and Roca: Pages 210-404, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Final Copy Sent to Press: Introduction- Page 125, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Final Copy Sent to Press: Pages 129-247, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Final Copy Sent to Press: Pages 248-336, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Final Copy Sent to Press: Reference Material, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)